[Music]
thank you
I've been reading your work for many
years and you are someone who's managed
to incorporate so many different fields
together at this point your free energy
principle can be discussed in fields of
mathematics physics biology it seems
you've managed to cross all these
borders and I think it's perfect for
this show
one thing I want to start off with is
when you think of the topic of the
mind-body problem you think of Rene
Descartes and he often said I think
therefore I am and you've now become
synonymous with I am therefore I think I
think let's start off with that because
I think it's beautifully poetic
considering this podcast is called Mind
Body Solution
yes I I do like that
um homage to uh Descartes
um so the the cheekiness of the reversal
uh is based upon the free energy
principle
um read as a physicist and effectively
this is a description a principle that
will be applied to anything that exists
um and the maths tells you that if
something exists in a certain sense and
then it can be read or interpreted as
making inferences so if you allow me to
equate inferring with thinking that
means to exist is to infer so if I am
therefore I think so that's the Genesis
it's one of those
um done that it's
um strange inversions yes you know uh
speaking to the slightly sort of
deflationary aspect of the of the free
energy principle you know it's slightly
tautological aspect I think at that
point it would be a perfect opportunity
to let's play with definitions let's
talk about three energy principle a
Bayesian brain and perhaps active
inference let's play around with these
definitions before we move to a
formalism of the free energy principle
right
um so they're all very closely related
uh so defining the free energy principle
first of all what is it it's just a
principle of the kind that you would
remember at school in physics like
Hamilton's principle of least action
um and as such it is effectively a
mathematical method it's a method or a
tool that you would apply to a
particular situation
and when applied to things like you and
me or in fact many other animate things
and biotic things
um one gets an interpretation of the
behavior of such things in terms of
active inference
um the inference part is just a
statement of sense making and
representation on the inside of the
thing uh where the thing in question can
be a person or a particle it could be
you or me
um and that sense making speaks to
making sense representing explaining
inferring the causes of sensory
Impressions from everything else from
the outside world
um and the best or the most if you like
inclusive way of understanding that kind
of inference and sense making when
applied to the brain would be the
Bayesian brain hypothesis so the
Bayesian brain hypothesis is the notion
that we can understand
our sense making and to a certain extent
with one commits to neuronal process
there is the underlying neurophysiology
neuronal Dynamics in terms of Bayesian
belief updating basically changing our
physical by physical States via
neurodynamics to represent probabilistic
beliefs bayesians of personal beliefs
probabilistic beliefs about the causes
of Sensations so that's inference
inference
um Loosely described under the Bayesian
brain active inference is the simple
move that you are acknowledge that the
sensations upon which you're basing your
inference are actively sampled you are
in charge of the data that is subtending
your inference and that sort of closes
the loop between you as an inference
machine a statistical organ or your
brain at least as a statistical organ
and and the world supplying that sensory
evidence of those Sensations and that
story and that sort of closing the loop
uh an action perception kind of cycle a
description of sentient behavior
um appealing to the Notions of active uh
sensing and active learning
um is one way of reading what comes out
of the free energy principle so that's
in my mind how those things uh oh let's
see how you triangulate amongst those
three Notions and when we think about I
mean obviously as you said they're all
very linked and when you think about the
free energy principle the formalism of
it do you think of energy minus entropy
and then you obviously go into different
aspects surprise Divergence then you
discuss obviously your internal States
hidden States action perception talk to
us about how this formula actually works
and how you do because a lot of people
have noticed when they question you
about this Theory everyone comes from a
specific field so if someone often tends
to attack you from a psychological
perspective someone tends to talk to you
from a biological perspective how do you
navigate all these territories and I
think with that I'd like to say that
you're one of the few people that I've
noticed who seems to be a genuine
polymath in that regard because you're
always able to answer these questions
succinctly with a lot of definitions and
just beautifully how do you manage to do
this
I have a lot of naughty and inquisitive
students so you get used to
answering questions uh after a while
um yeah that is again very very gracious
of you to say that
um but it's not I I don't think it's
um my wisdom
um I think that ability to jump from
um different disciplines or just take
different perspective or views on what
is probably the most important thing to
all of us which is how do we work and
why are we here
um is the gift of things like the free
energy principle and the free energy
principle I'm not claiming that that you
know the 300 is just the current
formulation of
um Millennia of thinking and physics and
psychology and philosophy
um and probably nearly every other field
including behaviorism economics and the
like so the whole point of the
preemption principle is that it is
um there to try and unify and to try and
Encompass and thereby endorse all the
various perspectives you can take upon
centered Behavior or Choice uh the uh
the imperatives and the right our
decisions
um you know right through where do I
look next in the next few hundred
milliseconds through to you know which
school should I send my children to and
so
the the
eclectic aspect that is brought to the
table by the free energy principle is
just due to its fundamental nature it's
it's a first principle account and by
definition if it is a first principle
account if it is applicable that it
should be applicable widely to various
phenomena red or looked at through the
lens of an economist or a psychologist
or a physicist
or or a philosopher
um that that it's interesting to say I
talk about things like surprised
information Theory and entropy and
um
intrinsic value you didn't actually say
that but I do talk about that
affordances and
the the whole charm of having a first
principal account that is sufficiently
simple to write down mathematically
is that you can see that the same
mathematical quantities mean
different things to different people but
they're all the same thing so perhaps
you know just to give you a couple of
examples of that underneath all of this
is just basically a description of the
states that I exist in those states that
are characteristic of me
so how would I express that
mathematically well I could just write
down the uh a function of any particular
state that reflected how characteristic
it was of me and that would be most
commonly written down as a log
probability of me being in this state
now any log probability is basically a
potential
and if it's a potential you can now read
it in by analogy to thermodynamics
um that log probability of being in the
particular state if I am me can also be
read as a statistician and you can call
that model evidence or in statistics
marginal likelihood if your information
Theory would be called self-information
and the average of self-imation is
entropy
um if you were an economist it would
basically be the states that I aspire to
it would be description of my attracting
set written as if you were
a theorist dealing with random dynamical
systems so now this same quantity now
becomes an expression of
um utility or value if you were
ET James you would call it a constraint
on the imperative to maximize the
entropy and so on and so forth so the
key thing
is that everybody's talking about
exactly the same thing it's just that
they've got different words from it so
the you know the joy of
um sort of seeing that
um Central quantity under the hood
being able to make sense to lots of
different people just is the
um an expression of the expiratory scope
of this kind of first principles account
so everybody's right they've just been
using different words
I I think you're absolutely right I
think when people try to develop any
Theory or hypothesis it's always very
important to sort of realize that we
don't exist in a vacuum there's there's
so many different fields of study that
are studying the same things but just
defining them differently
um discussing them very differently but
they all come together at some point and
any good theory needs to be able to
explain these various expertises as well
there needs to be some sort of a full
explanatory version of all of these and
they shouldn't be a gap and you manage
to bring these all together when you
talk about hierarchical Bayesian
inference it plays a very Central role
in your work and I remember when I was
reading about this and doing
computational Psychiatry as part of the
blocks during my masters I remember
coming across your work and thinking
this is so beautiful this is the way
you've managed to sort of incorporate
this into Psychopathology is even more
intriguing because I remember the first
time I read about it and you spoke about
posterior and priors and the way it will
dictate how someone experiences
hallucinations delusions and just
general differences in their field of
vision Etc
how did that come to you at some point
at what point did you manage to realize
that this Theory as a very active role
to play in mental health
all right
well the answer is another strange
inversion I'm afraid I started with me
um I started as a psychiatrist
um and a what used to be called a sort
of mathematical psychologist or what I
wanted to be a mathematical psychologist
and I think a clinical version of that
is exactly as you say a computational
psychiatrist that phrase introduced by
my friends uh Reed Montague and Peter
Diane um has only been around for about
half a decade but now we're all
computational psychiatrists so as a
young man I aspire to be a computational
psychiatrist so the free energy
principle is the denouement of
um that formalization but I think it's a
really important point you bring to the
table there
um and and I think there are two moves
you um have to make to to appreciate the
potential applicability
um of things like the Bayesian brain of
the three energy principle to to the
suffering of patients that you might see
in the outpatients the first move is to
have a physics of beliefs a physics of
inference a physics of sense making if
you like a physics of basic sentience uh
that is inactive so it has to be
sentient Behavior so it's all about
choices and decisions and how I move and
indeed
um how I control my autonomic reflexes
you know respond to my gut feelings and
exert from some personal control over my
physiology and internal learn
um so that's the first thing that you
have to have you have to have a physics
of sentence you have to have a
mathematics that connects the uh the
foundations of our Dynamics in a
physical world to the world of beliefs
and influence and sense making and
representation in this inactive sense so
that's the first thing then once you've
done that you can then say well okay
under what circumstances or what would
it look like if this inference went awry
was in some sense not fit for purpose of
the particular world or Eco Niche or
environmental
interpersonal relationship that this
person was having to infer and to learn
and to actively navigate to deploy her
active imprints for example
um and then you get I think to
computational Psychiatry but that does
depend upon
um committing to a view of all
psychopathology
as intrinsically some kind of false
inference
um but it's a very natural view that if
you just think about hallucinations and
delusions for example I mean what are
they they are effectively inferring
something is there when it's not so if
you were a statistician you say oh yes
that's a type 1 error that's just bad
influence because you've got something
wrong with your standard error but of
course you know that there's some direct
corresponds to the Precision in uh say
predictive coding variants of the basic
brain hypothesis
um which itself then relates to synaptic
gain and neuromodulation and certain the
actual certain drugs
um similarly all neglect syndromes
um or um in the old days would have been
called dissensitive or hysterical
syndromes
um
you know again read as false inference
which simply mean I'm inferring
something is not there when it is it's a
type 2 error
um and you if you think about all the
different disorders and ways of
suffering uh that people present with in
Psychiatry and indeed quite a lot of
Neurology as well there can all be casts
as some kind of false inference you know
um dysmorphophobias
um say anorexia nervosa having you know
false inferences about my body
and even simple things like uh parking
that simple but awful things
um but uh you know simple in the sense
the more motor and neurologically
oriented
um conditions like Parkinson's disease
you could think of as a failure to infer
and to realize my inferred intentions
that I am now about to move
so
you have made tumors first of all we've
linked physics to belief updating and
inference and then we've taken
um Psychiatry as instances of a kind of
aberrance or a kind of failure of that
influence and belief updating process
but I repeat put it in an inactive
context so you know you couldn't explain
Parkinson's disease unless you talked
about
um Banning as inference you know
treating movement and acting engagement
with the world as the realization of
inferred fans things that I am likely to
do next in in this moment or indeed
again choosing which school to send my
children to I still remember there was
one specific line that I quoted from one
of your papers I can't remember the name
of the paper but you actually spoke
about that phenomenon way
someone who's acutely psychotic
schizophrenic when you look at these
patients and you show them visual
illusions
you're able they're able for some reason
to see the reality of the situation
whereas we fall for this trick so in
those cases people often say that
they're seeing the real reality the
radical truth and we're not talk to me
about this phenomenon because I think
it's quite intriguing that they don't
fall for it but you with the free energy
principle with your theory you're able
to explain this
it's a fascinating area so that
um there are rare instances where
um Psychopathology or any pathology
um
um can actually improve certain
performance
um of course one has to qualify what one
means by improved performance but the
particular example you're talking about
I think is absolutely fascinating and
it's a resistance
um characteristically shown with certain
people either people on the Spectrum or
people with schizophrenia uh or schizo
typo
um approaches to life
um that renders them
uniquely resistant to the kind of
illusions that we all experience
um and it's just worth noting well
what's an illusion well it's a false
inference but why is it false it's
perfectly good from the point of view of
the person having the the inference and
having the uh presumed percept and
qualitative experience uh
however the experimenter you know the
naughty experimenter who's deliberately
after the stimulus in a way which is so
unlikely that they can now say no no
this is a false percept because I know
how it was caused and the subject I for
example have completely the wrong idea
the wrong influence about how it was
caused so it is a wonderful tool for
people in psychophysics to actually test
how our inferences can fail in relation
to the actual causes of our Sensations
but to put that another way around what
it does it's a beautiful Pro of the
prior beliefs that we bring to the table
so that you know going back to the
notion of the Bayesian brain read simply
that means that we have
um at hand a number of hypotheses that
can explain the causes of this pattern
of sensory or for example visual
information
and we generate these hypotheses
actively say predictions in predictive
coding and then we look at the adequacy
of these Protections in
um explaining the sensory data so
effectively little scientists we are
testing hypotheses against sensory data
and if they're not good at hypotheses we
will reject them and
um and revise our hypotheses and this is
the basic belief updating that we're
referring to previously but they
um that um that adjudication and that
updating rests upon your prior beliefs
before you see some sensory data
um relative to the Precision of those
data that are going to move your prior
beliefs to make them into post-drivilees
after seeing the data so we come back
again to this notion uh and a key notion
of the Precision afforded your pride
beliefs the way that you think the world
works or the way that these particular
sensory uh path of sensory stimulation
are generated relative to the evidence
at hand through that you're accessing
through your Sensations so
when people well suddenly when people
like me and you talk about
um this resistance to Illusions
um in people's African schizophrenia
what we are effectively saying is that
they have less precise or imprecise
prior beliefs that they're more
sensitive
to any sensory evidence at hand
so if Illusions are the things that
reveal our prior beliefs
and people with schizophrenia are
resistant to illusions that means they
don't have very precise primer needs and
that tells you an enormous amount about
the the message person the Dynamics and
the sense making in people who are
resistant to Illusions
um particularly in relation to how we
think the brain encodes that Precision
because you have to estimate the
procession doesn't come for free it's
very much like a statistician Computing
the standard error which is the inverse
or the component of precision it has to
be evaluated and if you get that wrong
you can
produce your type one your type 2 errors
all that false influencer underwrites
hallucinations and delusions but in this
instance
um a resistance to a particular kind of
um not a pseudo hallucination but a
particular kind of illusory person
I I think I'm glad we're touching on
this because this leads me into my next
question which which is surrounding
illusionism as a theory of Consciousness
when you think of an illusion as a
misinterpretation of a sensory stimulus
that does exist
um and you think of the theory of
illusionism Keith Frankish Daniel
Dennett Susan Blackmore lots of people
working and to an extent when you take
into account certain things that someone
like Anil sits is with perceptions being
active hallucinations
um you you sort of come to this
conclusion that okay the sensory
stimulus we're receiving sort of gives
us an idea a posterior belief at some
point that we have what is known as a
conscious experience a phenomenal first
person subjective experience sorry I'm
going to head into philosophy at this
point and then we'll try and get back
into the Neuroscience but at the physics
Etc so when you think of Dennis and all
these philosophers who discuss
illusionism as a theory of conscious the
basic premise is that we we are are
experiencing something uh however
because
let's say someone like you or Donald
Hoffman who takes Fitness payoffs over
reality the fact is we are never really
perceiving what is actually out there
we're just perceiving what is meant to
allow us to survive long enough perhaps
um to breed do whatever we have to do
and in this case Consciousness believing
we have some sort of an entity something
similar to an eon Vettel
um the fact that we believe this allows
us to go through life and successfully
reproduce and continue to thrive
do you think this has a lot of value and
do you think that these theories of
illusionism as a theory of Consciousness
has value using your theory of free
energy principle and the Bayesian brain
to back it up
well in the way that you articulated
them absolutely yes okay
um do you have any rebuttals against
that
not whatsoever
um no I I think you phrase up um in a
compelling uh way and um it fits exactly
with the view of uh a Bayesian brain and
you know more generally the free energy
principle
um your control hallucination
um is just an expression of the way that
sensory Impressions somehow control our
sense making on the inside and the
degree to which we let them control
depends upon the Precision that we
afford
um these sensory Impressions
um by definition will never actually
know what's going on on the outside so
the whole point of inferring is you
don't know the answer you're just left
with the best belief the best
probabilistic
um guess as to what's going on out there
there will never be any true access to
the causes of that and in a you know
sort of complementary fashion I will
never know what you are thinking I can
never know so I'm on the outside looking
at you and so you know it all including
the free energy principle in fact um as
applied to your brain this is just a
hypothesis it's just a belief you know
there is a fundamental divide that in
the physics application of the energy
principle rests upon something called a
Markov blanket but there's a a
fundamental divide an informational
barrier
um or probably you know beyond
information an existential barrier
between the inside and the outside of
any thinking thing and which means that
the the question is that what is what is
reality is there a metaphysics is is
unanswerable
um all you can do is
um I think an incest uh expresses it as
inference to the best prediction as
opposed to explanation
um but I think influence of the best
explanation is perfectly okay in terms
of explaining the world to yourself as
you
um sample it as as you send it
um one thing
um so I'm not a philosopher uh
yeah I am very naive and and however
um I did want to make a philosophical
Point here
um that we you know you use the phrase
We believe uh in some aspect of
ourselves
um
including the fact that we believe that
we have experiences there is an argument
that this is just another illusion it's
just another hypothesis that in fact
selfhood in and of itself is just
another hypothesis that these are sort
of illusions that we've been to the
table
to make parsimonious sense of the fact
that there is there appears to be some
coherence in my embodied interaction
with the world
um but it's not a necessary belief for
living and surviving and adapting and
I'm sure if viruses could tell you they
would deny having a sense of self
um so I yeah one night to argue that
Consciousness either the kind of
self-consciousness that you refer to or
just
um the notion that I am having a
positive experience you know if the kind
of um experience that people like Thomas
metzinger would associate with opacity
or phenomenal uh opacity
um these in and of themselves are still
just hypotheses they're just ways of
explaining my sense making in this
instance on the inside as opposed to
explaining what caused my external
sensory states does that make sense but
how this I think is entirely consistent
with you know with the views that you
you expressed I think it's it's sorry
for you continue call
well no you asked for a pushback
um
pushback I can think of
um and again forgive me if I'm I'm using
the wrong words but
um
the free energy principle inherits from
um the theory of sparsely coupled random
dynamical systems
um and the special case that emerges
when you have a particular kind of
sparse coupling between something and
everything else
um
if that is true it does have if you like
a metaphysical commitment that there has
to be something else out there so um
there is there is a sense that you can
um you can be a complete skeptic and
there is no reality
um uh from the point of view of applying
the free energy principle
um to my sense making or indeed applying
it to your sense making your sentience
um but the free energy principle of
itself starts from from a very
metaphysical uh position that there
isn't out outside and there isn't inside
um and what we're looking at is quite
simply a generalized synchronization
between the Dynamics on the inside and
the outside that can be read as
inference and belief updated
I think I think that's exactly where
someone like Daniel Dennett would break
away from someone like Donald Hoffman
exactly what you're talking about where
that it would suppose that there is is a
reality there is an external reality
however there's still no such thing as
phenomenal experience or conscious
experiences because we are crafting this
as we're going along we're interpreting
that way and that might not be the best
way to say it anyway whereas Donald
Hoffman then goes to the assumption that
all conscious experience is the reality
we're talking about and that might take
it a bit further because now there is no
external reality we're sort of creating
reality from conscious experience but
yeah he takes a different physical route
uh just called briefly what I wanted to
say was I mean I've got tons of notes
here I just want to show you a lot of
different things I've got a bunch of
equations here the main goal was because
I've seen so many different talks of
yours and so many different interviews
I've noticed how people tend to as I
said ask you questions based on their
expertise or their field of expertise
and I didn't want that to happen because
for the most part I'm so on board with
your view and I love the theory so much
that I used it in my own Master's
dissertation to defend illusionism so I
the dissertation is called psychiatrist
defense or illusionism has a theory of
Consciousness and a huge chunk of that
actually Incorporated your work yourself
call uh Chris frith and many others but
I was worried that when I get into this
interview I'm going to start defending
it even more and I did not want that to
happen so I made very specific notes to
Sidetrack me off off that path but
before I do leave that part the last
thing I do want to say is
if someone does ask you what
Consciousness is
how do you actually go about answering
that question do you find that you go
down it philosophical route or do you
stick to a neuroscientific psychiatric
Road
yeah but I think very much like you
um it would depend upon who I am talking
to and who is listening
uh it would be very context sensitive
yeah there are but yeah
if you're talking
um
to
people who are
um in a more physicsy world and they
they are interested in the in the
Naturalization of Consciousness I would
appeal to this
um well go right back to the your uh
Cartesian dualism how do you repair that
or should you repair that any other
there is actually an argument I've heard
recently from very valued colleagues
um that there is a neocartesia
cartesianism
um that emerges from specifically uh the
free energy principle on the one hand
and Quantum information theoretic
formulations on the other hand
um this is due to things like the inner
screen hypothesis by Chris fields which
is uh you know a fascinating
resurrection of the Cartesian theater of
a particular sort
um but if I was talking to to somebody
wanted to naturalize
um naturalize in relation into the laws
of physics writ as usually differential
equations or in Quantum information
theoretic terms I would be looking to
answer their question in terms of how
how do you how do you bridge these two
um the you know how do you arrive at
some kind of dual aspect modernism
um that's still preserved The Duality
but explain it
um and I would be talking about the
difference between a
posterior belief a Bayesian belief that
is encoded by the states of a brain for
example
and the probability distributions that
are entailed by the states of those
brains so you've got on the one hand
um an intrinsic
information geometry that inherits from
the probability distributions that
somebody in the thermodynamics as a
physicist would understand the kind that
we use in brain Imaging for example to
look at brain activations through the
expenditure of thermodynamic energy in
order to do neuro you know to support
neurodynamics
about exactly the same by physical
states are those that parameterize
another kind of information geometry
which is the information geometry of
beliefs the space in which I do my
belief updating moving one belief from
this point to this point because that
movement is important because most of
the
um much of the arguments that I would
engage with in terms of Consciousness
would
um frame Consciousness as a process you
know I think you mentioned that
explicitly what does that mean from the
point of view of trying to naturalize a
conscious process that was
quintessentially belief basis is
movement on some statistical manifold so
you do get that for free from the free
energy principle so it's you know that's
why I and a number of uh at least close
friends and collaborators uh use the
phrase you know a physics of sentience
sometimes if you don't want to be quite
so bold and sometimes as you get told
off for using the word sentence so but
at least you can talk about a physics of
information
um and it is that sort of link between
the information theoretic the belief the
statistical
um
um aspect of neurodynamics and the
thermodynamics that underwrite that
which does I think provide that link
between
um the the other men's well you know the
Cartesian dual dual aspects
um of um of
certain things like the brain if I was
talking to uh
um people
um in philosophy who are more interested
in
um you know phenomology I think you have
to address some hard questions about you
know
what would be the necessary properties
of a self-organizing self-evidence free
energy minimizing system that could
possibly support
um qualitative experience or
um qualia
um as uh and then you have to ask other
questions about
um when would there be some
self-awareness of this and um you know
issues of self-modeling of the kind
again
um addressed by people like uh Thomas
metzinger I about those kinds of
um conversations would take a slightly
different route and would focus on the
phonology and interestingly they come
back to the the Precision we were
talking about before if you remember we
were talking about
um having to estimate the Precision
which means that you've got
um
well for those kinds of systems or
creatures or particles and that have the
capacity to estimate the Precision of
their implicit beliefs and the sensory
evidence that is updating those beliefs
that the very Act of uh deploying those
estimates of precision and inferring
that Precision becomes a kind of mental
action so now you've got a way of
linking
um mental action read as people like
Jacob uh limouski and and Thomas
metzinger and that kind of
philosophizing
um with the psychological reading of
this mental action which is just
attention it's just basically
um deploying or affording more attention
to this level of representation in a
hierarchical context or this
um sensory stream thereby selecting that
for leap updating giving those sources
of evidence privileged access to your
um deeper higher level uh belief
habitating so you now you you're in the
world of Building Bridges between
attention mental action and filmology
and then you have to then you start to
talk to people who like to think about
self-hood and self modeling and
self-awareness
um and you start to think about well you
know how do these things unpack in terms
of the kind of generative models
that are necessary to Define model
evidence marginal likelihood variational
free energy what kind of models would
you need and you normally get to you
know very very deep models uh
hierarchical models where normally we
have in mind a sort of hierarchy or a
centrifugal hierarchy so you know deeper
is is usually sort of more abstract and
slower
um and um you know one normally starts
to think about well what kind of depth
would be required for me to have a sense
of self or first of all I have to be an
agent to be an agent I have to have a
generative model
um that entertains the consequences of
my action otherwise I can't plan so
immediately we're talking about
generative models entailed by certain
creatures or people that escapes the
moment simply now because I've got a
journey model of the future unlike a
thermostat or a virus I've now got a
very deep generative model of a
particular sword which goes into the
future it's future pointing but
crucially it's my future it's not your
future anything else it's just my future
what will happen if I do that so that
makes me into an agent so immediately
talking about a very special class of of
um
self-organization self-evancing
um and then you'll have to ask the
question well at what point do I
recognize that it is me that is actually
doing the planning and and why you know
you know yeah if you want to apply the
theology principle you have to ask the
question well what licenses this kind of
Deep
generative modeling
um and that's a pressing question
because the um you know I've used the
phrase self-evidencing I should just
very quickly
um qualify that which is a philosophical
term which I know nothing about in
philosophy but I do know that Jacob
Harry my friend in Melbourne is a
philosopher uh thinks it's quite apt to
use as a description of the the Bayesian
brain minimizing it's free energy
because if you remember the free energy
is synonymous with technically a lower
bound on surprise surprise itself
information but it's also the negative
model evidence or log model evidence so
as you're doing
um optimal inference you are implicitly
trying to maximize the evidence for your
models of your lived world so yourself
evidencing
um so
the interesting twist here is that
um you can you can easily show literally
on the back of a matchbox that the the
log evidence is equal to accuracy minus
complexity which means that every move I
make in every aspect of my brain
that is engendered during
neurodevelopment or indeed Evolution
that's to pay a price
for every more accurate explanation
illusion
um that um
that it
um deploys
and that prices the complexity cost so
it means you're trying to minimize the
complexity so why on Earth would
um say Evolution equip you and me with
this really deep generative model where
I've got all this extra complexity that
I can be in this state of mind on that
state of mind I can be anxious I can
mean that I can be frightened I can be
embarrassed and you know why would it do
that well of course if it provides a
parsimonious explanation
of my sense making and my active
engagement with the world then
um it pays its way in terms of the
um the the the increase in accuracy of
the kind of things I can explain and
engage with
um
pays its way or over
compensate sufficiently for the
increased complexity and then you ask
yourself what kind of Worlds would
potentially
um justify this kind of modeling this
kind of very sophisticated hierarchy
deep modeling
um and usually one ends up and now I'm
talking to people in neuroethology and
social Neuroscience you end up with well
the only kind of worlds in which I need
to infer I am me and I am in this
dispositional state
is in a world in which there are lots of
other things that are exactly like me
that have certain dispositional
intentional status in relation to me
otherwise I don't need this it would be
you know I'd have an overly complicated
model so you argue yourself into a
situation where this kind of
Consciousness it can only be present or
is only licensed under the free energy
principle in a world full of con
specifics and creatures and usually in
an encountered eatonish that depends
upon lots of other people so that now
becomes a slightly relational aspect uh
to this kind of Consciousness so I've
given you a I haven't talked about the
the the in a screen hypothesis but there
is another quantum physics version of
this so there are lots of different
stories you can tell depending upon what
people want to hear Carl you touched on
so many different ones there I love the
last one because it reminds me of Chris
Fritz work and and he loves to talk
about this social and relational aspect
of Consciousness you guys have written
many papers together and someone else
you've written with is a colleague of
mine from South Africa a very good
friend Mark salms you guys have also
written together and I know Mark takes
us down to a more basic level of
of existence in terms of conscious
experiences coming from more basic parts
of the brain what got you guys to write
here then how did you guys sort of get
together and do this these beautiful
papers together
right well I just mentioned both Chris
and Mark in that um so interestingly
um when I um as a young psychiatrist got
into brain Imaging and it was at exactly
at the same time that Chris was Chris
fifth uh aim
um from basically clinical uh psychology
and neuropsychology that was one of the
world's certainly the UK's experts the
schizophrenia research he came to join
us at the MRC Cyclone unit in the very
first brain Imaging also in the mission
tomography studies of people with
schizophrenia so we you know he's been
my mentor and friend for since the
Inception of my academic career and and
is still meant to be writing the last
paragraph of the last paper that I've
tried to submit at the moment uh Mark
but um there's an interesting connection
and
um comparison between Mark and and Chris
Mark I met later in life at
International conferences and was very
impressed with in those days his
encyclopedic and
um very embracing knowledge of Freudian
ideas
um in relation to psychoanalysis but
also neuropsychology and so he's one of
those polymaths
um who can transcend different fields
you know he can he can write volumes on
Freud and yet uh bring the most
informative and puzzling
neuropsychological cases to the fore to
events some very deep questions about
you know how we experience our world and
you know how that can be expressed via
things like neuropsych analysis so um
the interesting thing is that Chris
really hates Freud
but they're both they're both committed
to understanding the brain as an organ
as a social organ and uh but as you
write this say uh Mark is much more on
the sort of you know
um
it predicates his work on the
neuropsychology and the neurobiology
um whereas Chris is much more in terms
of the dadic and the social and social
Neuroscience aspects
um that underwrite
um you know sense-making way it matters
um uh but both of them at the end of the
day I I try to understand that you know
the patients they saw as young men and
perhaps Mark is still seeing patients I
don't know
um so that that's how I got involved uh
you know Mark's ideas yeah I think
you're absolutely right they um
they are
um more grounded in the wet wear that
um that would have this um that would
endorse certain
um psychoanalytic psychic therapeutic
psych neuros and neuropsychological and
psychiatric readings
um and interestingly he's happened upon
um exactly the same
um
Focus that I suspect your computational
Psychiatry thesis
focused on so you know again we come
back to this key notion of precision and
uncertainty and of course you know if
you want a you know to naturalize uh
psychopathology
it's all about beliefs and if you want
to what is definitive of a belief well
it has clearly uh when thought of or
when when read as a probability
distribution it has an option an
attribute of content in terms of the
location parameters but more importantly
it's got a an attribute of uncertainty a
dispersion that's the whole point about
a belief as opposed to a point estimate
so if we are creatures that deal in
beliefs then the you know the challenge
that we face is basically evaluating and
knowing and representing our own
uncertainty either personally or some
personally you know and indeed
um you can see this throughout say in
economics you know the markets have lost
confidence there's in you know things
that matter are usually those the
confidence the uncertainty that I that I
hold my beliefs with
um so that that I I keep using the word
uncertainty because there's a lovely
little phrase that Mark has celebrated
his most recent book that you know the
Hidden Spring and subsequent sort of
academic Publications which is this
notion of felt uncertainty so he thinks
that feelings
uh all about the estimation of and
deployment of decision and uncertainty
in exactly the same way that we ended up
trying to naturalize
um resistance to Illusions in people
with schizophrenia it's all the same
thing so so he puts a very heavy weight
on that
um to the extent he gets very cross when
people become cortical Centric you know
they think it's all all in the frontal
lobes there's no he says no he's
literally deep in the hierarchy
literally deep in the cells of origin of
these really powerful neurotransmitter
systems that do the attentional game
they do the neuromodulation they set the
Precision they balance and coordinate
our our belief updating and of course
that fits very comfortably with what
we've talked about before which is a
mental action read as attention being
able to get some control over those
um Dynamics and belief update businesses
that basic mechanics
um what's going on inside our head
so when I mean you guys both of your
papers I remember you you all sort of
culminate and get together with this
idea that this Bayesian brain this this
is fundamental to what we do when you
think about perceptive experiences we
realize that at some point my red sunset
and your red sunset are not the same
um is a very two different experiences
both comprised of different neural Euro
factors different social factors
different experiences in the past so
even time plays a big role this comes
along well when you think of Markov
blankets because you think of these
different internal States
um different active States perhaps for
each person who's thinking
how do you find Marcus blankets play
let's first talk about how Marco
blankets to play a central role in the
free energy principle and how this sort
of navigates across different areas from
physics to chemistry to biology to
psychology
um let's go to economics Etc
right I thought you were going to talk
about
um synchronization across Markov
blankets and communication to get to
that at some point
uh excuse me so um yeah as you say the
the mark of blanket plays a foundational
role in the physics reading of the 300
principle where you have to before you
can start to talk about anything you
have to be able to demarcate and Define
what you mean by something
um and the first move is
um to individuate that thing from
everything else how do you do that well
you simply identify those states that
intervene between everything else and
the thing in question they separate the
internal States Dynamics paths
narratives
um
technically
um you know these would be States in a
state space
um from the point of view of say um a
large van equation or
um some kind of statistical physics
um and the
um what transpires is that you if you
want to individuate the state's internal
to something from the state's external
to something then one way of doing that
and one could argue the only way of
doing that is to demonstrate that they
are conditionally independent if you
want to be able to separate there has to
be some kind of probabilistic
separability there has to be some kind
of Independence but it's conditioned
upon the Markov blankets so what does
that mean well this basically means that
um you and I or more specifically your
brain and my brain
um are not closed systems we are open
systems and our systems are open to our
Niche or our environment or our heat
bath if you were a physicist
um but that kind of openness is
um the kind that preserves that
conditional Independence between me on
the inside and everything else on the
outside and that's where the Markov
blanket comes in and then you can
um for most things
partition the Markov blanket into two
sets of states the active States and the
sensory States and semantics are rather
obvious in the sense that it's just
making a distinction between those
states that mediate the exposure of the
inside to the outside so the influence
the vicarious influences of the outside
on the inside and those have been the
sensory States and then to complete the
circle to induce the necessary kind of
circular causality we need for the
synchronization we're going to talk
about you have to have the other side of
the street
um which is the active states that
mediate the influence of the internal
states on the external States
so you've got this rather delicate
fundamental sparsity structure where the
sparsity is read in terms of the
influence that one state has an on
another state that foregrounds a special
set of states that are called blanket
states that come
um be divided into active and sensory
states that intervene between the
external internal States
um the inner screen hypothesis we were
talking about before inherits from a
Quantum information theoretic
formulation of this notion where you can
look at this blanket as a screen onto
which I can write say the environment or
the world out there writes onto this
blanket writes onto this holographic
screen and those become my Sensations
and I can then read those Sensations
from the holographic screen on the
inside and then I can double back so
that the environment senses me through
my actions so there's a if you like one
level of perfect symmetry between the
two and that's symmetry
um is just
um so that symmetry is advanced by
um the minimization
um of free energy in the sense that if I
can predict what's going on out there
and what's going on out there is at the
same time in some sense trying to
predict what's going on inside my head
the ultimate the free energy minimizing
solution the most likely solution just
brings us back to you know being in
characteristic States for the
environment and the need but so we're
talking just about a description of a
generalized synchronization or
synchronization of chaos
um between two sparsely coupled
dynamical systems with the special
structure that allows me to
preserve my conditional Independence so
in a sense the uh the um The Illusionist
perspective we were talking about before
is a must it can't be any other way if
you define existence as conditional
independence from the world in which you
are immersed but of course there has to
be a world in which you are reverse so
you can't take that too far in terms of
a skeptical position yeah when you think
of Markov blankets um in the context of
let's say neural networks
um how could the concept of Markov
blankets be used to better understand
flow of information or computations
within a neural network
is this applicable and are there any
specific applications we could utilize
this concept to enhance our
understanding of
Consciousness neural connections Etc
yeah I think I think there are it's
interesting that you should ask that and
what you should do is get
um Maxwell Randstad and Chris field and
possibly even Mark I mean Mark Mark Sims
has also been involved in these
conversations and another other people
I'm sure they will also suggest so this
group have
um
been thinking for a year or two and are
currently submitting papers to things
like the general Consciousness studies
and elsewhere that rest explicitly on
um halving the internal dynamics of a
brain in terms of nested Markov blankets
I'm trying to ask the question is there
something unique about a Markov blanket
on the inside in your brain which you
know may be physically very distributed
um but statistically well defined that
could possibly support Consciousness so
this is the inner screen hypothesis that
I mentioned before so your question you
and perhaps you've actually said seen a
preview
oh well it's a very it's a very
impressive to astute question then
because this is exactly what people are
like Axel and Mark and Ken and uh David
and everybody else would love Chris
would have loved to have been asked um
yeah so that's the whole premise that
that well first of all it's this stand
back
um so you're right to ask yo are Markov
blankets useful
um yeah I think I think that they are
foundational and they're used implicitly
every everywhere I mean not only are
they foundational in the sense that they
um they Define Your Existence and my
existence and anything that we uh that
we engage with or we think we engage
with
um but they are implicitly you used
whenever you start to
simulate or reproduce
or emulate any kind of sense making or
intelligence artificial or natural
um you know whether you're playing with
neurons neural cultures in a dish they
are the cell membrane is a Markov
blanket that you know defines a cell the
connectivity of the neurons defines
another scale of Marco blanket or a
marker plug into another scale which
says that this is a network uh not
exactly the same maths applies to neural
networks and machine learning and
artificial intelligence research and the
operation of your iPhone or Google
search machines
um so these things become practically
really important in defining the network
of a thing that's doing the
um the you know the computations of the
information processing in a pragmatic
sense and indeed you can read these
active and sensory States as the inputs
and outputs to anything that is doing
some kind kind of computing
um so they are essential
um in defining things like say one human
architectures you know we do not you
know you and I don't use a value but not
connection but you can still use
knock-off blankets to Define them but
even if you look at the kind of uh
architectures
um that we use
um for sense making in the hierarchical
Bayesian brain or hierarchical
predictive coding
um story then the message passing that
is required to do the belief updating
becomes tremendously efficient due to
the presence of these and carefully
self-maintained self-evidencing Markov
blanket structures so remember the mark
of blanket rests upon a sparsity
structure it's what the connections and
the influences that are not there so
that means that you can now do local
computations if you can Define the
Markov blanket of you uh you may be just
an element of your dendrite dendritic
tree you may be a synapse you may be an
entire dendritic tree you may be a cell
you may be a brain region you may be
Compass you may be an entire brain you
may be having a type person or you may
be a family you may be a species you may
be an institution you may be a biosphere
you know and every every scale the same
rules apply
um whereby you get the efficiency from
um the sparsity where the sparsity
underwrites the very structure and the
ability to actually dissect at every
scale and the system at hand so that
leads to an IEP that's practically
really important when you're designing
neural networks or chips you you need to
keep all your computations as local as
possible and you do that by using your
Markov blanket
um if you wanted to if we return to
um the implications for
um belief updating in a brain
um then just saying the phrase
hierarchical predictive processing or
hierarchical basic inference
immediately commits you to a certain
class of Markov blankets because the
hierarchy is just defined in terms of
the connections that are not there so
each hierarch level possesses a Markov
blanket that separates its superordinate
level from its subordinate level
so just talking about hierarchical
structures is just one special case of a
particular kind of nested Markov blanket
and then we get to is there a special
Markov blanket so now this is the Crux
of the paper that you have read that I
thought you had I'm looking forward
well I'll send you well I'll ask you
know if you email Maxwell ramstead and
Montreal he'll send you
um he'll send you I've only got a copy
with all the authors redacted so I'm not
quite sure who the authors are at the
moment
um I'll take up that option I'll take up
that offer and definitely do that no
he'd be delighted
um so the other the idea of um
one of the key ideas
um that fits very comfortably with
um the ideas from Chris field and people
like Jim glazebrook and Mike Levin
um which is this inner screen hypothesis
is that there is one irreducible Markov
blanket there is one that you can't get
inside and find any hierarchical
structure or any partition
so
what would that mean if there was one or
more possibly but there was certainly at
least one irreducible Markov blanket in
my brain it would have some quite
profound implications
um it would mean that it could never see
itself other than acting on the outside
which is the rest of the brain so the
only way you can solve evidence is by
engaging in mental action
and now you ask well what kind of mental
action would it engage
um would it uh what did the executive
systems the active states of this
particular minimal Markov blanket they
are precisely the cells of origin of the
neurotransmitters that Implement
Precision control and attention so we're
right back with Mark Sims again but
we're in a very comfortable position
because not only are we friends with
marked zones but we're also friends with
everybody who talks about things like
higher order thought Theory so predicate
the entire argument on this hierarchical
structure which means that at some level
and usually it's the higher level or the
deeper level uh don't do interesting
metacognition
uh things start to happen that you could
associate with uh with conscious
processing but this is exactly what the
minimal Markov blanket uh irreducible
Markov blanket would say it is something
that is deep within a hierarchy that
cannot there is no higher or deeper
level because if there was you'd be able
to partition the internal States within
that minimum Markov blanket it also fits
very comfortably things like the global
neural workspace Theory I mean what is
global and what is a workspace well it's
something where you can share stuff so
you can't further subdivide it and it's
firmer because it sees everything so it
has it has a lot of construct validity
in relation to a game where we started
everybody's right but they just got
their own way of expressing it
um but in this instance we are or one is
expressing it explicitly in terms of
individuation separability read through
the lens of the free energy principle in
terms of Markov blankets
crucially in a scale applied a
particular scale and this scale is the
scale of brains so this argument
wouldn't work when you're trying to
describe the weather or Evolution it
wouldn't just work when you're trying to
describe things at a Quantum level or
indeed um at the level of a um your
single neuron or neural population this
kind of argument is scale is tied to a
particular scale but it has if you like
a scale free aspect in the hierarchical
uh in the hierarchical
um
partitioning that induces the notion of
a non-partitionable or irreducible
Markov blanket so funnily enough that
that notion of the irreducible Markov
blanket being the inner screen is
exactly the new Cartesian theater that
we're talking about
that's very fascinating I mean I'm
scheduled to chat to Mike living soon
and I had no idea uh I think I should
send him an email to Chad about this you
said it was Mike Levin Mark storms Chris
Fields who else was there was one more
name you mentioned the theaters the
inner screen hypothesis that
um if you like survives
um a Cornerstone for this more
Collective inclusive effort to try and
get you know what value of I should call
it a minimize a minimal unified model of
Consciousness that includes people like
Mark zones and and Kenneth and Wilton
and uh David Rudolph and lots of people
um
yeah sort of organized by Maxwell
ramstead um and Chris Fields is a really
important player in that but the inner
screen hypothesis in and of itself
um does indeed um uh is is indeed due to
um uh Chris fields and his friends and
particularly Michael Evan and people
like uh Jim glazebrook so that that that
formulation is another if you like
access which I you know you'd have some
great conversations with both Chris and
Mike
um so they come at this from the point
of view of
um sort of basal cognition the notion
that everything is effectively
um can be cast and possibly even is just
a process of information you know is
this information processing and
self-organization just is
um
the uh the processes that evolve that
effectively do believe updating or
process information using classical
information
um you know when it comes to sort of the
kind of biotic self organization that
might Levin deals with so he you know
he's famous for Zen inbox and all sorts
of really insightful takes new takes on
um cellular and
um and
um
your biological self-organization
um you know some of my favorite ideas
are you know if you'd that you might
like is that you know
when when you appreciate that sort of
you know
um physics and this is the Chris Fields
quote and there is no bright line
between sort of physics biology and
psychology they're all the same things
um but just using different words and
and Mike takes this to his extreme or
used to is is got more sophisticated uh
in the past few years but uh several
years ago he had this notion that
um cancer was a was a delusion a
delusion that arose from a pathology of
basal cognition which I think is what
you know cells are failing to infer know
their place their failing to infer that
no I shouldn't be growing in this
context because it's delusional I should
keep on growing and of course he's
absolutely right uh so you can even get
a computational Psychiatry of cancer out
of this but it does require a commitment
to think about all self-organization as
basically a process that have made red
as an inference presence under a belief
that basic dating process the right kind
of processing and
um
bounding self-information and and
entropy read from the point of view of
information Theory Chris fields's
particular take comes from uh his skills
with Jim glasbrook in Quantum
information Theory so that's that's
where the information theoretic aspects
come and then you can start to talk
about the relationship between the
principles of unitarity and in
tanglement and the like and what that
means when read
um or what it means in terms of a
Quantum formulation of the classical
reading of the free energy principle
that doesn't normally deal with Quantum
you know it usually starts with uh you
know classical mechanics with all the
defender formulation I'm like
I just I love so much about what you
just said because we when I talk about
it I often think about the same thing I
often call ourselves
receiving persons organized by
organelles crafted by cells designed by
DNA manufactured by molecules assembled
by atoms forged by Fusion over forged by
Fusion via Stella supernovae so this is
a saying because I think if you don't
incorporate all these things together
you're just you're missing out an
opportunity not to reduce things to the
nothing but aspects but rather to grow
the complexity of what we're talking
about you just increase the scope of the
conversation so much more by discussing
every realm of reality and I think you
get that and you seem to be working on
that from that perspective as well
absolutely and that that again I think
that's a
yeah I love the way that you actually
expressed it you should definitely get
Chris Fields uh on on your podcast
because his big thing is that scale
freeness that's scaling variance
um that you know and in fact I was on a
call literally
um about two hours ago where he made
um I thought a delightful point that
um because the free energy principle is
by construction scale free it cannot be
reductionist at the same time so it is
quintessentially
so what you just expressed I think
covered all those scales
um and I think that's part of the well
saying it has to be it has your your
formalism has to be skill free it has to
be devoid
um for me mathematically in the spirit
of the renormalization group it has to
be deployed time and time and time again
um and as soon as you realize that then
you start to answer the D or ask D
questions about you know top down
causation between scales so as soon as
you've got a scale free Theory then it
can apply either to camera oscillations
in your hippocampus or it can apply to
Natural Selection red as Bayesian model
selection and then you start to ask big
questions well how does this very slow
self-evidising process contextualize and
be informed by this very fast
self-evidising process or information
processing in a way that is emerging
from just having these same kinds of
processes unfolding uh with a separation
in this instance temporal scales so you
know Chris would wax lyrical for a long
time about this so perhaps you can get
Chris and Mike together then you I think
that's a real idea I think I should
start doing that I know I know the last
time I think you Kurt and Mike I think
spoke together as well if I recall
correctly I can't remember yeah yeah
because I wanted to ask you when you
think about this project that everyone's
talking about
um and Markov blankets do you think that
because some systems are so complex how
do you find do you think there will be
any sort of indirect or hidden causal
relationships that might hinder this
from happening what what sort of
applications or techniques should be
employed to effectively identify Markov
blankets within complex systems
all right
um yeah
so this is a very sort of practical uh
uh issue
um and it would be very nice to be able
to sort of parcellate the brain for
example or parcelate
um an institution or a you know uh
you know an economy
um to be able to identify the uh the the
different Markov blankets um given some
empirical data
um there is a worked example of this
which is little known because it's just
so complicated uh it's almost impossible
to read but I wrote it and I'm quite
proud of it
um and it it I think it was in uh
Network science but it was exactly the
challenge of taking brain Imaging data
with
um thousands hundreds of thousands of
measurements of activity over time
and then parcelating it at different
scales so it was exactly what we're just
talking about it was creating Markov
blankets of Markov blankets and Markov
blankets I'm doing it in a way that was
empirically uh constrained by measuring
the connectivity and it you know at its
sparsity to imply where the market
blankets were and then once they've got
a Markov blanket those now constitute
the Intel states with a bigger Mark of
magnet and then you can sort of carve up
the entire brain successively course
from Corsa
um spatial scales and what was really
interesting
as a phenomena that um is if you um
I was going to say immersion but in fact
it's actually baked into the you know
the uh the renormalization group that
you would access mathematically
um that we would use to access the
scale-free behavior at least formalize
our naturalize it
um that things get slower as they get
bigger so you could actually we could
actually estimate the time constants of
the neural fluctuations and implicit
belief updating associated with
different spatial scales
ranging from a cubic centimeter or
millimeter or so of a brain through the
entire frontal lobes and then we can
extrapolate out to very very big things
and very very small things now look at
the characteristic time scales it was
just implicit by scanning through the
time scales by having lots and lots you
know literally a hundreds of thousands
well at least a thousand uh a thousand
little Markov blankets all jostling
together uh partitioned uh and they're
moving to say a hundred of them and then
to ten and it's by extrapolating you can
then think about sort of collections of
brains pen brains or a tenth of a
um a cubic centimeter of the brain right
the way down to to the quantum scale and
let's look at the different time
constants that they were engaged so that
was a really interesting academic
exercise but did rest as the same being
able to identify uh Markov blankets
um what you're asking though
um is you know is is a key issue in
terms of complex system
um analysis and modeling uh being able
to carve the system in the right kind of
way
um in order to
um usually to simulate it in a way that
allows you to do forecasting or scenario
modeling and the like or uh projecting
uh a response to a therapeutic
intervention and say a clinical
Neuroscience or Psychiatry through to
weather forecasting yeah getting the
right course grading the right Markov
blankets in plain is absolutely
essential there are lots of people
working on that at the moment one email
exchange event this week is from a
gentleman called Jeff Beck who's taken
on the very deep challenge
of considering Markov blankets that
wander around
so one interesting aspect of
a simple definition of a Markov blanket
is that it depends upon
um a probability distribution and that
exists over a non-trivial amount of time
but if you think of something like a
candle flame
that is moving
um and furthermore the constituents the
molecules and the ions that constitute
the plasma that is the surface of the
the flame is it fair to say that the
flame has a Markov blanket given all its
contest constituent molecules I.E other
small scale markup blankets and
continually being exchanged and um
moving wandering around so he's taken on
the challenge of of taking Markov
blankets into this sort of
um more liberal domain and dynamic
domain and see if one can still apply
the free energy principle in in a
practical way but to do that he has to
have at least simulations or numerical
studies that allow him to actually
identify Markov blankets that move like
waves in certain uh in certain media so
that's still I think an outstanding
problem which a lot of people well when
I say a lot a few key post callings
looking at and I think it's a very
useful company of inquiry that's quite
fascinating it's great to see that so
many different people are working on
this at this point because when you look
online and you look at the amount of
citations I mean you are one of the most
cited neuroscientists on the planet and
it's great to see that a lot of people
are taking these Concepts seriously and
trying to roll with it looking ahead to
the Future what directions or
advancements do you anticipate in the
study of Markov blankets for example
except for the one you just mentioned
and
where do you think the free energy
principle is going from here
um I think there are probably
um
three directions of travel
um and we've implicitly we've already
covered the most important ones in our
conversation and so you know the first
um
one is indeed computational Psychiatry
and computational uh neurology I mean in
a sense all
um the work that Christopher and I and
many other colleagues put in um you know
decades ago into understanding
functional brain architectures via brain
Imaging was in the service of your
ultimately asking questions about
neurology and Psychiatry and much of the
theorizing that led to active inference
and the free energy principle inherited
from the data analytic and modeling that
we were applying to uh to make sense of
brain Imaging data I realized at exactly
the same principles could be applied to
the brain on when I say realize we're
told by people like Jeffrey Hinton you
can apply exactly the same principles to
the brain the health helps machine
um so um that's one that's one direction
of travel I think it's just uh again I
use the word naturalizing and I recently
learned what it means and I think it's
you know a useful phrase to to
naturalize Psychopathology in a way that
you can write down the laws and the
maths and you can start to creating
silico patients and digital Twins and
intervene on them uh without actually
um you know giving drugs on uh
psychotherapeutic interventions to
patients until you've shown
um and to a certain extent that that
style of approach is um already starting
to bite not under in the context of the
free energy principle explicitly but
certainly
um in the modeling of things like
epilepsy you know have it having having
naturalized pathophysiology say you know
the transmission of epileptic discharges
and seizure activity in the brain uh to
the extent you can actually put it in a
computer and start to do weather
forecasting of this particular person's
brain and what might happen if we did
this and that I think that's one very
exciting Way Forward uh another
complement of that um sort of Applied
application of the free energy principle
um would be the ability to phenotype
people so there's a phrase computational
phenotyping which which I quite like
which basically means being able to
characterize this person or this cohort
um in terms of the parameters of their
generative models that they use to
explain their world
and that provides a really powerful and
efficient summary on this person and the
in terms of their beliefs and their
belief updating and their prior
commitments
um and being able to to be able to
measure and quantify somebody in that
kind of way can be very very useful not
only in terms of tracking responses to
therapy but also just getting the right
there's allergies the right way of
carving up
various psychiatric conditions and their
etiologists because now you've got a
naturalized process Theory under the
hood so that's one kind of thing the
other direction of travel I think is in
artificial intelligence
um just actually building so practically
what the 300 principle brings to the
table
um is not really a pretty first
principles account of uh existence and
sentient behavior
um but practically another strange
inversion another strange inversion
um instead of having to um instead of
having to understand the system in terms
of its Dynamics as you would the complex
system modeling
um you're trying to understand the
underlying mechanics by saying well
these Dynamics this set of say
differential equations looks as if it's
performing a gradient flow on this
lipunov functional this
uh lagrangian and I'm going to try and
estimate what this um what this
underlying potential function is that
causes my Dynamics and a simple
explanation for the complex system I
want to understand
um for me of course that's always going
to be this surprisal or the the uh
the log marginal likelihood or the free
energy balance on that
um
but what you can do is if you know that
the the Dynamics of your complex system
and always be expressed as a gradient
flow on a free energy functional
objective model where the gender model
just scores or articulates
characteristic states of being that you
want to um you want to emulate then what
you can do is you can just write down
the free energy functional of your
preferred states of being and then just
integrate the system to reproduce the
sentient behavior that you would have
seen if this thing existed and had these
was attracted to these characteristic
States so it's a really powerful way of
building machines that look as if they
exist in a particular way and of course
that's the aspiration of machine
learning and artificial intelligence you
know
um and so
it's only in principle you could deploy
the 300 principle in the context of
building artifacts that do the right
kind of belief updating by the right
kind of course I mean uh being able to
model their world where their world is
it's basically the world of users
basically you and me which brings us to
the third direction of travel which is
um the kind that Chris fifth would like
which is you know the explicit
acknowledgment that what is really
interesting here is this scale free
application of 300 principle where
you've got lots of different free energy
minimizing self-evidencing Markov
blankets all living in Markov blankets
over a different scale in institutions
and theologies and now ideologies and uh
you know with ethnic bounds and and all
that so how does that unfold and how do
you get the right kinds of ecosystems
that have this joint free energy
minimizing behaviors that does not
um incur upon or require certain Markov
blankets to be vitiated or destroyed you
know so what what we're talking about
now is the physics of an ecology that
has sustainability
at its heart or at its core because the
whole point of the free energy principle
it's a description of systems that have
an attracting set and how they sustain
themselves within that attracting said
so I would imagine that the 300
principle will be useful and indeed
pursuing that through colleagues that
and versus AI
um
uh so my colleagues in Industry
um this this is one application the free
energy principle in the service of
um in you know underwriting in a
principled way the aspirations of all
right-minded people engaged in designing
the next version of the world the World
Wide Web or artificial intelligence or
Information Services and speak not to
growth that speak to sustainability that
you know a biomimetic take on
sustainable ecosystems but in this
instance ecosystems of intelligence so
that was a bit hand wavy but it's yeah
it really is a fascinating game when you
start to talk to people who are actually
in charge of engineering uh the next the
next web there really is so much
potential um there's something I wanted
to ask and I forgot about it earlier but
I was thinking about Markov blankets and
how they they played this role
um to sort of just
differentiate between let's say it can
sort of play a role between
differentiating between the self and
another in a sense does it have any role
or impact when it comes to free will
how to incorporate these ideas together
um
it might sound good on your side
good
continue
with your audio
um
no no sorry I was having issues
I couldn't hear you
hold me now it's back it's back hey
sorry
all your questions okay so
when you think of Mark of the United
States
[Music]
um
but irrespective
and sequence
um
uh
foreign
foreign foreign
I think that sort of brings me to
something I wanted to ask you from the
very beginning with the free energy
principle in mind what do you call is
the meaning or purpose of life
as well
that doesn't really have too much of a
um
that question has no meaning uh so so
from the point of view the participants
observing the universe that was
comprised of things what will not the
free energy principle is saying is that
if this universe is
um settling onto an attracting set and
if they're all like a tractor then it
must be the case that it is
um on average maximizing the GMB
attractive characteristic States it's
just like rolling to the bottom of a
bowl that's it
um what way of reading that road into
the bottom of the goal that convergence
to
um the
active set
um is in terms of a minimization of
thermodynamic free energy
the special thing that's brought to the
toe by the 300 principle is the
insertion of the markup blanket now you
can read the minimization of further
environmental energy
in terms of a minimization of certain
beliefs inputs where the beliefs are
held by internal States but they are
about external States so this is before
I I phasing like that because of your
purpose
so yeah that's the energy principle
gives you a
um what people like loves to custom and
Maxwell Randstad would require a basic
mechanics which is exactly the same as
simple mechanics exactly the same as
statistical mechanics exactly the same
spot mechanics
so this particular physical state has a
meaning in the nation represents it's
expanding it's a hypothesis about it is
a lot of this external State about
something else this illusion illusion of
what might be out there
um
so I think that
he has
if there is life in the sense of that
thank you there is an emergent meaning
and that means found in the internal
dynamics of life and it's meaning uh is
established in a relational sense of The
Simpsons uh the um the relation
um
um of the internal sense making
um the measurement if you know Quantum
physicist or whatever is causing things
divisions and Sensations that you are
using to do your measurement so this is
a positive
um
information Theory which I'm completely
subscribed to and um so that would be
one way of doing it I think it's
slightly more
um obviously popular as the question
would be well what's the what's the
meaning in my life where I am on this
Julia systems that has its capacity or
agency in the sense that I have precise
Dynamics and I have the ability to model
the consequences of my action in this
very particular case where I can now
infer what I am going to do in the
future
whereas something called expected for
reality
so you can you can compute the
probability of a particular narrative
action path uh trajectory into the
future as
um basically a
um
any soft Max uh function obviously
called expected theology so
the path to the Future that has the
lowest expected for the energy is the
most likely that I will follow that will
select
very well I will select the path that
has the lowest expected of the energy
and what does that mean an expected for
energy in the same way that you can
Express log evidence as equal to
accuracy minus complexity
you can express the expected free energy
as the expected information being minus
the expected cost where the cost is a
surprise that negative self-evidence has
caused the a
um uh a characteristic state so if you
know they'll get other characters feel
unbreakable and very poor dead
dissipating
um then that would be very surprisingly
highly costly so you've now got two like
affordances or imperatives or patterns
that you can select
um which is
um which is why what I have reading at
the meaning of life to be you know what
it's my likely think what it's purpose
what is my purpose well it is the um it
is the imperatives are underlying the
things I choose to do what do I choose
to do I choose those things that
minimize my expectations
I will try to choose those things and
maximize the expectation again or
minimizing the expected cost the
expression information going it's just
curiosity
so the meaning of life for me
assuming that I'm avoiding all those
constant states of being
myself in danger of the world very much
it's such a problem with my wife
um that the majority of behind me is the
Curiosity it's it's basically uh be a
scientist yeah yeah
I think I think that's a that's a
beautiful way to put it Carl
um there's there's so many things I want
to ask you about but something I often
love to us my guess is and I think it's
because this gives us an idea of how you
were crafted as a thinker and how you
really developed this I think over time
if you had to give us a Mount Rushmore
of your favorite
philosophers or scientists
who comes to mind instantly who are
these people who really guided your
thoughts growing up and made you the
manual today because I'm pretty sure
when people look at your work today you
from the time when time moves on we're
going to be talking about you have a
feeling the same way we talk about some
of the greats and I think it would be
great to know who inspires Carl Preston
right yeah
I think that's a great option
uh but what I think sort of the two
people
um
um when I read or reference with with
warm feelings and a tinge of excitement
um especially when I find their quotes
um uh our um helmholtz and Feynman
um Herman Von helmhansen and Richard
Simon Simon um look the helmets
reference that makes sense I mean when
you think of unconscious inference and
all your work it makes a lot of sense
what about these guys really get you
going
well
you're going about people like Mark Sims
and possibly me um I mean he was a clear
polymath I mean you know if you just
think about every move you make on
certainly every move I make in my little
world
um in trying to naturalize psychology
and psychopathology and and
more generally sort of you know what
makes us tick and um you've come across
some foundational idea or principle or
decomposition that he is brought to the
table so you've mentioned the notion of
unconscious inference I mean that's just
basically uh debating brain uh as
beautifully articulated by
um Peter diam and Jeffrey hinton's
helmets machine in in the um the the
early 90s
um so that's certainly one thing but it
doesn't stop there uh yo you you look at
his work uh you know in perception
generally you know he had all the
one aspect of an illusion uh
illusionists thinking at least
and anything that was worth saying you
know at some point he even said it but
more than that of course you know um you
know the helmholtz notion of um free
energy and the contribution to
thermodynamics is also pretty Central to
what we're talking when I'm the kinds of
things I talk about
interestingly right down to something
called the helmholtz decomposition which
I suspect you probably won't know about
if you're more interested in
computational psychotic so this is a
this is
um an expression of the fundamental um
theorem of um
um what is it back to calculator no
variation I can't remember my part is
anyway the helmholstery composition just
means that what you can do is describe
any Dynamics in terms of two effectively
orthogonal Parts one part is dissipative
and it climbs Hills or climbs downhills
like the ball rolling down the hill
um this is the thing that generates
energy it's a thing that does basically
palpitating in an information
theoretical free energy principle uh
context
um uh and the other part is called the
conservative part also in a solenoidal
flow and this part if you like
circulates upon ISO Contours of
potentials or probability distributions
so this is if you like uh can be read in
many many different ways if you're an
engineer it's a decomposition of
um procedures that you would use to
assimilate data or estimate
unobservable state to do inference as an
engineer and using say a kelman filter
and you would have a prediction so given
my beliefs about states that what are
our private section about what I'm going
to sample next and that will be the
conservative solenoidal part and then
you would have your update which is
basically a prediction error awaited by
its Precision which changes my
prediction my Prime relief
um and that's the if you like the uh the
dissipative part that's my engagement in
the world that's that was that's what
takes energy and does the belief
updating but that is written down
mathematically very beautifully by the
helmets decomposition and what it tells
you
is that if you've got this if
um by appeal to the helmhouse
decomposition you've got this solenoidal
flow then you are necessarily breaking
something called detail balance
of the kind that you see in open systems
and non-equilibrium systems so there's a
direct mathematical mapping between the
helmet's decomposition and the class of
systems that physicists use and study
which largely in the past few centuries
has been sort of um
systems closed systems at equilibrium in
this Century it's now all about
non-equilibrium systems and that
non-equilibria aspect is just due to the
conservative part of the helmets
decomposition also it is exactly the
thing that makes Us lifelike it's what
equips us with life cycles with
biorhythms with oscillations in the
brain at every scale of gamma
oscillations and our favorite
hippocampal dendrite through to
um your Beating Heart and respiration
through to our sleep wake diurnal Cycles
through to our life cycles
through to the orbit of the you know of
the heavenly bodies all of these that's
not quite a biological uh aspect
certainly for for biological systems
that that break detailed paths and have
this particular kind of itinerancy while
still
um maintaining their integrity and a
free energy principle
um then you've got a description of
biotic self-organization the foregrounds
oscillations and rhythms and recurrences
returning to the states I was once in
which of course is you know part of this
sort of keeping yourself within within
characteristic States so I've gone on a
little bit there about how I know you
can you can see why you said you're such
a fan of helmets I mean it's clear
you can see the joy in your face when
you're talking about this and it's very
fascinating work as well so it makes
sense why this really gets you going and
Feynman what about Feynman really
because Feynman I'm a huge fan of
Finance work
um sometimes even for fun I end up
watching fireman lectures just just keep
home at night
yeah yeah so what yes it's the one side
so detainment that that I can enjoy my
wife watches as well my wife is a nurse
and not into into the physics uh
but yeah no he's he's a very alluring
personality
um but you know
if you didn't know this
um it's probably worthwhile just saying
out loud I mean the variational free
energy was his invention
um so he was trying to
um well one reading of the history is
that it was his invention you could have
good arguments with um Russian
mathematicians that can get at
compression and um free energy
minimization from the point of view of
algorithmic complexity via things like
uh soft uh induction and the like
um and certainly there is a school of
thought that really celebrates that sort
of
um compression view of
um that is described by uh free energy
minimization
but the final view is is much more um
more closer to my academic training and
and
um
inheritance
um so what he was trying to do was to
solve exactly The Impossible
marginalization problem that people
would try to solve if they wanted to
engage in exact base and inferencing
exact sense making the exact statistics
to actually get a grip of the
um the the very best explanation of this
metaphysical world that of course
doesn't exist
um but that's intractable in the same
sense that he couldn't possibly
integrate over all the paths of small
particles say an electron would taken
Quantum electrodynamics
um he couldn't possibly
um normalize that probability
distribution by integrating over all the
universe you know of paths you know a an
electron could take
so what he did was to dissolve that
problem by converting this inference
marginalization integration problem into
an optimization problem and they did it
by creating this band on the quantity he
wanted to optimize namely the margin the
log marginal likelihood which is the
variation free energy
so that's that that you know all of the
free energy principle owes a you know uh
um its greatest debt I think that's not
quite Fair on help health and everybody
else right through from account through
to uh
um
all the way through well everybody yeah
I'm sorry people you couldn't mention
but anyway certainly from a technical
point of view
um that you know that that that that
pathological formulation is so beautiful
um uh and EO it is leverage directly
certainly in my personal work and the
way that I would formalize the free
energy principles I'd be elevated to you
know you could read the free energy
principles as duel to James's maximum
entropy principle uh but in the you know
when read or writ as a uh yeah in its
pathological form that is really a
homage to firemen's original conceptions
but as you say it's such a delightful
person to watch as well yes and and like
me it was a committed smoker so I like
that yes you love your cigars I know
that the uh I often think about that
video of Feynman
um where he's talking about a red flower
I think it was and and he says his
friend his artist friend looks at this
looks at this flower and then tells him
you as a scientist you're obviously
going to break this down and ruin it and
he's like no no it's actually because
I'm a scientist I'm going to look at the
cells beneath the flowers I'm going to
look at every single flow of each atom
he's going to look at every single
aspect of this flower and so much
greater detail that it only increases in
its its complexity and beauty and to him
the flowers far more beautiful because
of this and that goes back to what we
were talking about earlier and I think
that's something that you guys have in
common
it's beautiful because fireman has that
perfect way of blending the science with
the art and that brings me to this
question I wanted to ask you when are
you going to make or write a book
because your work is so complex to a
point where most people really don't
know how to approach it when it comes to
whether it's a neuroscientist
psychologist physicist if they don't
understand the work they're going to
find it very difficult have you ever
thought of writing a book that is a bit
more for the Layman out there
yeah uh well
um no I I'm notoriously bad at writing
um accessible
um those horrible kind I think would be
required for uh for a book and so I'm
probably not going to uh what I've found
tends to work best
um is to
um have the next generation of people
who are much more fluent usually either
um because they're sort of in a a
person-facing kind of uh
um science like psychology or medicine
uh
um or they've had a philosophical
training so I find these these people
are much better than I am and
articulating in prose in narrative form
and the ideas so they can write the
Books I'll just sit back and buy I did
try once um so foreign
Robert Pryor MIT press who
um has been uh asking me for at least
three decades uh when I'm going to write
the free energy principle book and he
thinks he's got precedence because his
surname is prior uh so so he thinks any
book that appeals to the page especially
the free energy principle has to be
commissioned by him and he was
absolutely right but the problem is
there is stuff I can write is so uh talk
to us and I have to say that you know as
with the free energy principle itself
with its emphasis on complexity
minimization only providing a
parsimonious explanation the 300
principle becomes simpler and simpler
the longer it marinates certainly in my
head so I you know I've taken now every
year now I write a paper
um you know describing how a simpler
version and a simpler version that
process will go on at some point it may
be sufficiently simple to be attractive
to Bob Pryor or any other editor who
invites me or asks me the question that
you've just been asking my suspicion is
uh I will probably be retired or die
before before that arrives so um you
know but there are some wonderful
um
uh Renditions of the free energy pro and
con
um and certainly uh most recently the
active inference book by Thomas Parham
Giovanna pazulo uh you know I actually
say it there that you know I was allowed
to write the forward but nothing else
um yeah that's okay I was just about to
ask you what are some of the reading
recommendations I think that's
definitely one that's on top that's
actually a book that I want to read
desperately
um and I cannot wait if you had to
recommend us any other books what type
of books
would you recommend to either increase
our knowledge with regards to the free
energy principle or active inference in
general or just books here that you find
help a scientist philosopher
in general to grow in this field
um
I'm afraid I'm not going to give you a
very good answer to that there's a
there's a reason for that there are two
reasons
um one I don't have time to read books
um as when you get to my age
um you you you you tend to be you get
asked to write blurb for books uh so I
have to speed read certain chapters of
books but I don't actually have time in
my
um working life to read books I can only
review papers and and scientific
proposals that's even working seven days
a week
um
any papers that come to mind oh there
are lots of papers yeah but I I'm not
going to say I'm not going to tell you
what they are because they're the people
I don't mention will be very very upset
um so I'm I'm not very good at sort of
reading books nor recommending books so
what I'm going to do is is
um what my but my father is so he
sometimes sends me books to read which
which he thinks are good for me so I'm
just going to mention the last one that
I read literally in a couple of weeks
ago which is algo land yeah
I really like that
um so that would I would certainly
recommend that and I think that had kind
of written written that
um last year as opposed to I think 2014.
there would have been more emphasis
because the free energy is just that you
know that Viewpoint I think articulated
slightly more in a classical setting in
a particular pathological formulation of
Richard Feynman
um so I really enjoyed that but
otherwise
um if people are generally said there
are lots of wonderful papers usually by
philosophers usually by again people
like Andy Clark and Jacob Howie and and
Maxwell Randstad
um uh you know when he's wearing his um
his philosophy at
um but there are also lots of really
wonderful other but you just go to a
repository so Baron has got a nice
repository in GitHub of his favorite MEP
papers there's something called the
active inference Institute run by Daniel
Friedman uh that is dedicated to trying
to organize the material in a didactic
or pedological uh way they're actually
writing now I think another active
inference book which is an explainer for
Thomas's and Giovanni's actually in
principle so if you're interested I
think you go to the people who actually
know how to teach and uh and and
articulate these ideas it's funny
because one of the last people well this
was actually a year ago now that I think
about it who talks about hierarchical
Bayesian brains and active info it was
Lisa Feldman oh yes yes and one of the
books yes exactly and the book she
recommended was alkaline and this was
just when the book came out so it's
funny that you both basically talk
around the same topic and recommend the
same book so it clearly is an impactful
book in general
well she's also written some very
influential stuff in the emotional
sphere and as now
um you know so quite quite a key player
in the active inference that's certainly
the emotional inference and intercepted
at princefield along with anneal Seth
and and colleagues yeah just a close-up
call
um any theories of Consciousness the
brain that you feel
sort of go against the free energy
principle anything that you know stands
out that counter argues this principle
in a way that does sort of get you get
your Shield up
um no I'm afraid not but I think that
probably affects the fact that I don't
have a philosophical training so I don't
you know I'm not used to adversarial
progression uh adversarial argumentative
approaches
um no I I don't you you know the whole
point of the free energy principle is it
has to explain everything or it explains
nothing
um so if there is a viable Theory Of
Consciousness out there there has to be
some way of if you like reframing it or
um substantiating That Right theory uh
by naturalizing it using the free energy
principle remember Predator principle
can never be wrong so it doesn't need to
defend itself it's just a method or a
tool very much like I'm trans principle
inherently unfalsifiable
yeah yeah and I think um just I'd like
to say thank you so much for all your
work I clearly supported in the fact
that I I quoted you a couple times
referenced you numerous times
um so to me it is replicable it is work
that a lot of us are using out there so
from my side I just want to say thank
you so much I call it it's a pleasure
it's an absolute honor to actually chat
to you and yeah I really enjoyed this
conversation
well so am I you've asked some really
excellent questions
you've kept me on my toes but also kept
me smiling thank you very much
[Music]